בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is נ. nun. We are
going to be wrapping up the third פרק perek and beginning the
fourth. And we start... we continue at the very bottom of מ"ט
עמוד ב', mem tes amud bais, after having had a lot of
fascinating גמרא Gemara yesterday relating both to proper שידוכים shidduchim between different
segments of the community and then the going into the issues about
attitudes towards עמי הארץ. amei ha'aretz. And we continue now seven lines
from the bottom at the two dots. וכן מי שיצא, V'chein mi
she'yatza, the line starts with the word שיצא. she'yatza. So here is
the debate about the משנה Mishna compares realizing you have חמץ chametz
left in your house and having to go around and destroy it,
but if that's not feasible, defined by either that you're going to
do a מצווה mitzvah and you don't have time to get back
to the חמץ, chametz, or you're going to save people in danger
and then you don't even make a חשבון cheshbon whether you'll have
time. So then you do ביטול. bitul. And at the time we
mentioned that there it's very clear that that is the one mention
of ביטול bitul in the entire all of the משניות Mishnayos of
מסכת פסחים Masechet Pesachim as a last resort, and that otherwise you
have to go you know the focus is on destroying it and
that's how you address the biblical concern of owning חמץ. chametz. Later
in the Amoraitic period just repeat what I said yesterday the גמרא
Gemara said הבודק צריך שיבטל, Ha'bodek tzarich she'yevatel, which basically means let's
always do ביטול bitul as a backup and then it becomes that
the ביעור biyur becomes questions well why do we then have to
do ביעור? biyur? But in the משנה Mishna ביטול bitul was a
last resort because it makes it a little bit of a farce
but anyway that's what you do if you can't go back. And
it said similarly this question about do you have to go back
or not go back is when you're taking meat out of ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, meat of a קרבן korban of a שלמים shelamim that you're
only allowed to eat in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. And as soon as you
step out of ירושלים Yerushalayim you have to burn it. So it
becomes פסול pasul I should say and the Rabbis say you burn
it in ירושלים Yerushalayim or in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Again
תוספות Tosafos points out if it was קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim like
a חטאת chatas then biblically you'd have to burn it in the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash because it's קדשי קלים kodshei kalim it's rabbinic
and therefore the Rabbis said if you've already gone too far, which
is past a place that you can no longer see ירושלים Yerushalayim
from where you are, you don't have to turn back but if
you haven't gone too far you can still see ירושלים Yerushalayim you
have to turn back bring it back into ירושלים Yerushalayim burn it
in ירושלים Yerushalayim burn it in or near the בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash. And then the question that the משנה Mishna turned itself to
was how much? When there are these scenarios that we described that
you would have to go back. You're not going for דבר מצווה.
devar mitzvah. You're still not in the case of the חמץ chametz
or you're still not you can still see ירושלים Yerushalayim in the
case of the meat of the קרבן. korban. Let's say it's only
a tiny little bit of חמץ chametz left in your house a
tiny little amount of meat. How much do you have to go
back for when we say you have to go back? So there
was the debate whether it was a כזית kezayis or כביצה kibeitzah
or difference between the two. So that's where we pick up. Okay.
So Rabbi Meir said it's only if it's a כביצה kibeitzah of
both you have to go back or of either and רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda said a כזית. kezayis. So the גמרא Gemara says למימרא
l'meimra this means to say דרבי מאיר סבר כביצה הוא דחשיב, de'Rabbi
Meir savar kibeitzah hu d'chashiv, Rabbi Meir thinks presumably thinks that a
כביצה kibeitzah is a significant size ורבי יהודה סבר כזית נמי חשיב
ve'Rabbi Yehuda savar kezayis nami chashiv and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says
no even a כזית kezayis is significant enough to make you go
back. ורמינהו Varamineihu I'll ask you on this. עד כמה הם מזמנין,
Ad kama hein mezamnin, what is the minimum amount for which you
need to do a זימון zimun if you've eaten bread?
So עד כזית ad kezayis the minimum is a כזית kezayis that's
the first opinion which is presumably Rabbi Meir. רבי יהודה אומר עד
כביצה, Rabbi Yehuda omer ad kibeitzah, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says no
no it's a כביצה. kibeitzah. By the way it's interesting that it
says עד. ad. עד ad makes it sound like you're going down
to a כזית kezayis down to a כביצה. kibeitzah. The Vilna Gaon
has a brilliant read of this which I'm forgetting which had to
do with a certain size of like a loaf of bread that
then you'd divide amongst the מזמנים mezamnim and it works out I
don't remember his read but there is a problem here that it
says עד. ad. It should have said כזית kezayis not until which
means like it sounds like you're going in the opposite direction. Anyway
so there is the debate also the question is does this mean
focus on זימון zimun or is it the minimum amount for ברכת
המזון? Bircas Hamazon? Again the גמרא Gemara seems to talk about ברכת
המזון Bircas Hamazon but it is possible to read this around more
specifically around זימון. zimun. Anyway the גמרא Gemara points out that although
as we'll obviously see in a second you could distinguish between the
cases it's a little bit ironic that in our משנה Mishna Rabbi
Meir says a כביצה kibeitzah and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says a
כזית kezayis and in this משנה Mishna they reverse themselves that Rabbi
Meir says a כזית kezayis and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says a
כביצה. kibeitzah. So how do you explain that? אמר רבי יוחנן Amar
Rabbi Yochanan מוחלפת השיטה. muchlefet hashitah. Yeah okay it's reversed one of
them one of the texts is wrong you gotta switch the switch
the names. אביי אמר לעולם לא תיפוך, Abaye amar l'olam lo teipoch,
no no don't run to that answer you don't switch the names.
התם בקרא פליגי הכא בסברא פליגי. Hasam bikra pligi hacha bisvara pligi.
There they're debating based on a פסוק pasuk here they're debating based
on like another issue sort of a you know a rational argument.
התם בקרא פליגי, Hasam bikra pligi,
there they debate on the פסוק. pasuk. Rabbi Meir סבר savar ואכלת
v'achalta how do you interpret the פסוק pasuk ואכלת ושבעת וברכת? v'achalta
v'savata u'veirachta? ואכלת זו אכילה. V'achalta zu achilah.
That means the act of eating. ושבעת זו שתיה. V'savata zu shtiah.
Yeah, that's the act of drinking. And ואכילה בכזית, v'achila b'khazayis,
so then the תורה Torah emphasizes ואכלת. v'achalta. ושבעת V'savata is coming
to teach you something else, not the literal sense of being satisfied,
but presumably to eat in a way that satisfying is accompanied with
drinking, and the act that requires ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon is an
act of אכילה, achila, and אכילה achila is בכזית. b'khazayis.
תוספות, Tosafot, as they say, אכילה כמות שהיא achila k'moshehi or whatever
it's called, you know, how do you know which way to go?
אכילה Achila standard is כזית. khazayis. רבי יהודה סבר ואכלת ושבעת. Rabbi
Yehuda savar v'achalta v'savata. No, no, no, no, let's read it like
פשט. pshat. אכילה שיש בו שביעה, Achila she'yesh bo svia, it means
an eating that leads to being sated. So the experience—the act or
maybe the experience of ברכת המזון birkat hamazon that obligates ברכת המזון
birkat hamazon is an eating that is a sufficient eating that brings
about satiation. ואיזו זו בכביצה, V'eizo zo b'khabeitza, that's already not a—I'm
sorry—זו בכביצה, zo b'khabeitza, that's already not a כזית, khazayis, it's a
כביצה. khabeitza. Doesn't sound like a lot
to fill you.
Right.
Well, what it means is that no teenager would ever be biblically
obligated.
Most people.
So anyway, if you take a look at תוספות, Tosafot, by the
way, תוספות ואכלת זו אכילה. Tosafot v'achalta zo achila. נראה דהני שיעורי
ככזית וכביצה דלא הוי אלא אסמכתא, Nireh d'hani shiurei k'khazayis u'khabeitza d'lo
havei ela asmachta, כמו שפירש הקונטרס, k'mo she'peirash hakuntres,
okay, בפרק קמא מי שמתו. b'perek kama mi she'meiso. So either one,
basically תוספות Tosafot says really they agree that to really be biblically
obligated, you really have to be, you know, sated, that even the
כביצה kabeitza position is not that. The question is, the way תוספות
Tosafot and רש''י Rashi in another place read this is at a
rabbinic level when we sort of speak about minimums that are A:
more objective, and B: at a lower level, we're not going to
speak about being fully sated. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda will say,
okay, so we'll go back to a כזית. khazayis. Whereas רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir will say, no, we'll speak something that's more symbolic of
being sated and we'll speak about a כביצה. kabeitza.
Okay, I think I reversed that. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said a
כזית khazayis and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda still wants it to be
symbolic of being sated and speaks about a כביצה. kabeitza. הכא בסברא
פליגי, Hakha b'svara pligi,
and here they debate based on another argument. דרבי מאיר סבר חזרתו
כטומאתו, D'Rabbi Meir savar khazartu k'tum'atu,
that you go back for it based on the minimum amount of
טומאה. tumah. מה טומאתו
בכביצה, Ma tum'atu b'khabeitza, the same way טומאה tumah is by a
כביצה. kabeitza. Now we mentioned before that there's a debate, do you
need a minimum size for something to become טמא, tamei, or according
to some, the כביצה kabeitza is not the minimum to become טמא,
tamei, even a tiny bit can become טמא, tamei, a כביצה kabeitza
is the minimum size to pass on טומאה. tumah. But either way,
the idea is that
כביצה kabeitza is significant. אף חזרתו בכביצה, Af khazartu b'khabeitza, so you
go back for כביצה. kabeitza. Now again, the interesting thing is that
that applies also to the what do you call it, to the
חמץ, chametz, not just to the קרבן, korban, right? רבי מאיר אומר
זה וזה בכביצה. Rabbi Meir omer zeh v'zeh b'khabeitza. But the point
is neither of them have become טמא, tamei, I mean even the
קרבן korban didn't become טמא, tamei, it just became פסול pasul because
it was taken out of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay, but the point is
by presumably yes, but you know, one thing that's very common amongst
קרבנות korbanot is a concern of them becoming טמא tamei and so
on, and that's a minimum significant size. And supposedly you'd have to
argue, although the גמרא Gemara isn't spelling it out, is that by
פסח Pesach as well, you know, the idea of פסח Pesach as
food and as אוכל, okhel, so you go by a size of
a כביצה. kabeitza. But it's not really so clear why, you know,
why this idea of a כביצה kabeitza because again the קרבן korban
isn't טמא, tamei, it's not really a relevant concern immediately by the
חמץ. chametz. But somehow that's what he says, that you look at
another size that has significance for this object. רבי יהודה סבר, Rabbi
Yehuda savar, רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda's position is more understandable, כאיסורו חזרתו
כאיסורו. k'issuro khazartu k'issuro.
Why would you look at the minimum for becoming טמא? tamei? Look
at the minimum for when it becomes forbidden to be eaten. מה
איסורו בכזית, Ma issuro b'khazayis, the same way you can't eat חמץ,
chametz, you transgress with a כזית. khazayis.
You have איסור issur of כל שהוא kol shehu though.
I understand, but fine, we're not talking about חצי שיעור. chatzi shiur.
The שיעור shiur of significance is a כזית. khazayis. And also by
a קרבן korban that is פסול, pasul, it becomes אסור assur to
be eaten, and the שיעור shiur of significance is a
כזית. khazayis. אף חזרתו בכזית, Af khazartu b'khazayis, so therefore when you
return, you return for a כזית. khazayis. Maybe one way of saying
this is that one focuses on a problematic act that you could
do with it, and the other focuses on the significance of the
object. Okay, that for an object to have significance, right, when we
say כזית, khazayis, that doesn't mean oh it's a different type of
an object, it's an olive's worth. But when we do find a
minimum amount makes us think of the object differently is a כביצה.
kabeitza. That's where we say, oh, now it's considered like a food
and that it can either receive or pass on טומאה. tumah. Right?
So that's not an act that I do with it, that's like
the object itself has greater weight and significance. Whereas a כזית khazayis
doesn't mean maybe give significance to the act,
but it says if I eat it, that's an act of eating,
and it makes the act significant. So one says you're returning because
you've got some חמץ chametz and you've got some meat, when... you
have when is that considered a significant amount of food? When it's
a כביצה. k'beitza. The other says no, but look, you could inadvertently
eat the חמץ chumetz or you could inadvertently eat the meat and
therefore even if it's a כזית kazaies you're in a problematic zone
and therefore you have to go back and destroy it. That's how
I'd like to read the debate.
Your brain's just, your mindset just works all the time. Yeah. It's
like no way around it.
You don't think you don't like that explanation?
No, the trouble is I do.
Look, I wouldn't have said it other than it makes no sense
why we're going to a כביצה, k'beitza, what the relevance of טומאה
tumah is to this discussion. So that's why I'm explaining the כביצה.
k'beitza. So I think that that might be a way of understanding
this debate.
Did you have a chance to find out about that בר מצווה?
bar mitzvah? Oh, no I didn't get a chance. I'm sorry but
I'll still try to check into that. Okay, so תניא tanya we
learned a ברייתא. braisa. רבי נתן Rebbi Noson אומר omer זה וזה
ze v'ze כשתי ביצים. k'shtei beitzim.
You don't go by כזית, kazaies, you don't go by כביצה, k'beitza,
you go by two ביצים. beitzim. ולא הודו לו
חכמים. v'lo hodu lo chachamim. Okay, so no explanation on any of
that. Where is that שיעור shiur coming from? I have no idea.
All right. Now we end since we just had a certain amount
of אגדתא agadata on yesterday's דף, daf, we end today's דף daf
with a good amount of אגדתא agadata tying in רש"י Rashi says
to the idea that it talks about going back to ירושלים Yerushalayim
so a little bit relates to the idea of what ירושלים Yerushalayim
will look like לעתיד לבוא. l'atid lavo. It also could be
that
we are coming to a close of I would say one segment
of the מסכת. masechta. The first three פרקים prakim really form a
unit that that are focused on the issue of חמץ, chumetz, right?
How getting rid of your חמץ, chumetz, making sure your dough doesn't
become חמץ, chumetz, how do you identify it to becoming חמץ? chumetz?
It's all about the חמץ chumetz concerns. Okay? The last פרק perek
is all about the ליל סדר. leil seder. The middle section is
all about קרבנות. korbanos. And then the fourth פרק perek which we're
about to begin as we'll see starts about some practices ערב פסח,
erev pesach, not חמץ chumetz related but practices ערב פסח erev pesach
and then becomes a whole פרק perek devoted to issues around מנהגים
minhagim which becomes fascinating. So the fourth פרק perek sort of stands
by itself. So that might be why we end this whole first
three פרקים prakim with even more אגדתא. agadata. Let's take a look.
Okay. והיה ביום ההוא v'haya bayom hahu it will be on that
day לא יהיה אור יקרות וקפאון. lo yihiye or yikaros v'kipaon. There
will on that day of the of the Messianic time there will
no longer be the light of יקרות וקפאון. yikaros v'kipaon. So whatever
those two words mean. What does that usually translate as? I don't
know. I mean I don't think that there's an there's an obvious
translation here. I don't know what your English says on these things,
but let's see
they don't bother to translate it. Okay, fine. So there will not
be any light of יקרות וקפאון. yikaros v'kipaon. מאי יקרות וקפאון? mai
yikaros v'kipaon? אמר רבי אלעזר amar Rebbi Elazar זה אור שיקר בעולם
הזה ze or sheyakar ba'olam hazeh this is light that this world
is very dear meaning like you know nice strong sunlight something that
we give a lot of weight and significance. By the way, like
יקר, yakar, you know, is weight, right? It's it's heavy. Okay. וקפוי
v'kappui and it's a light interesting the metaphors here of heavy and
light.
He says heavy clouds are יקרות yikaros and thick is קפאון. kipaon.
Fine. Okay. So anyway this is the light that nowadays is given
a lot of weight like the nice good strong sunlight. וקפוי לעולם
הבא v'kappui l'olam haba in the world to come it'll be very
lightweight. It'll be that that you call light? The light will be
so amazing and obviously there's presumably it doesn't just mean light it
also means light as a metaphor, you know, the sort of divine
light will be so amazing that the light nowadays that we give
weight will be extremely light in the world to come.
Does that mean
like minimal?
It means lightweight. Okay. קפוי kappui means to float. It means something
that's light and that floats. It'll be a featherweight. Look at רש"י
Rashi gives you the references. Okay. Aramaic it means it's an Aramaic
word for floating.
I thought קפוי kappui is like frozen?
Okay so look at רש"י. Rashi. רבי יוחנן אמר Rebbi Yochanan amar
אלו נגעים ואהלות elu negaim v'oholos this is the tractates of נגעים
ואהלות Negaim v'Oholos which are seen as the most challenging section of
all of ש"ס. shas. When רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva sometimes tries to
get involved in discussing אגדתא agadata some you know they say back
to him they say עקיבא מה לך אצל אגדתא כלך לך אצל
נגעים ואהלות. Akiva mah lecha etzel agadata kelach lecha etzel Negaim v'Oholos.
Okay. You know עקיבא Akiva you got some strengths אגדתא agadata isn't
one of them you need to go talk about נגעים ואהלות. Negaim
v'Oholos. So נגעים ואהלות שיקרן הן בעולם הזה Negaim v'Oholos sheyikaran hen
ba'olam hazeh they are very weighty and dear you know these are
the really challenging things to this in this world to learn those
tractates. וקפוין הן לעולם הבא v'kappuyin hen l'olam haba in the world
to come they'll be lightweight. Everybody will know נגעים ואהלות. Negaim v'Oholos.
חדר cheder kids will know that. The level of learning will be
at such an amazing level. ורבי יהושע בן לוי אמר v'Rebbi Yehoshua
ben Levi amar אלו בני אדם elu bnei adam these are people
שיקרים בעולם הזה sheyekarim ba'olam hazeh in this world they're given a
lot of weight and honor. וקפוין הן לעולם הבא v'kappuyin hen l'olam
haba in the world to come they'll be lightweights. Okay now that's
talking about like people of you know sort of of wealth and
of power that are not righteous people so in this world they
get a lot of honor and prestige but in the world to
come they're nothing. כי הא ki ha and this is a famous
story דרב יוסף בריה דרבי יהושע בן לוי d'Rav Yosef breih d'Rebbi
Yehoshua ben Levi רב יוסף Rav Yosef the son of רבי יהושע
בן לוי. Rebbi Yehoshua ben Levi. ben Levi, חלש, chalash, he became
sick, ill, even potentially deathly ill, ואינגיד, v'isnagid, he fainted.
ואינגיד v'isnagid could mean even something more like he actually thought that
he had died and then he came back to life. Again, I'm
not necessarily miraculously, like happens every day in the hospital. כי הדר
ki hadar when he came back, when he
was brought back to his senses, אמר ליה אבוה amar lei avua
his father said to him, מאי חזית? mai chazit? So his father
assumed that since he was like dead for a few seconds, his
heart stopped, his pulse stopped, he had some vision of the world
to come. You get that nowadays, right? People say that they had
some vision when they were dead for a few seconds. So what
did you see? אמר ליה amar lei he said to him, עולם
הפוך ראיתי. olam hafuch ra'iti. I saw an upside, a topsy-turvy world,
an upside-down world. עליונים למטה ותחתונים למעלה. elyonim l'mata v'tachtonim l'ma'ala. The
ones that in this world are at the top, in the world
to come are at the bottom of the heap. And the ones
that at this world at the bottom of the heap are at
the top in the world to come. So this world, somebody's powerful
or whatever, they get a lot of respect. Somebody is poor
and doesn't have a position of power or prestige, but might be
a tremendous צדיק, tzaddik, might be one of the ל"ו. Lamed Vavniks.
So in this world everything is upside down. In the world to
come, it's reversed and obviously gets set straight is the point.
No, he's saying that the world he saw was reverse of this
world.
Okay, so but which one is the right world? Okay, so אמר
ליה amar lei so he said to him,
בני beni my son, עולם ברור ראית. olam barur ra'ita. You actually
saw the right world, you saw a clear world. The world to
come is the way that the respect and the prestige that's deserving.
It's this world that is topsy-turvy. ואנן v'anan and then he said
to him, that's interesting. So the father then said to him, and
we, sort of Torah sages, היכי התם, heichi hasam, what's our status
there? So he said back to him, כי היכי דאיתינן הכא הכי
איתינן התם. ki heichi d'isinnan hacha hachi isinnan hatam. The same way
we're here, we're over there. Actually ברוך השם baruch Hashem we are
given some respect in this world and we're also given respect in
the world to come. So the rabbis do okay. It's the ל"ו,
Lamed Vavniks, it's the private צדיקים tzaddikkim that are quiet and nobody
knows about, those are the ones that are and the ones that
don't get the respect that they deserve. ושמעתי שהיו אומרים v'shamati shehayu
omrim and I heard when I was there that they would say,
אשרי מי שבא לכאן ותלמודו בידו. ashrei mi sheba l'chan v'talmudo b'yado.
Praised is the one that comes here and has his learning in
his hands. Meaning so entering into the עולם הבא olam haba with
a lot of learning under your belt as we would say it,
is going to give you is going to be give you a
lot of status, will be a nice entrance ticket for the world
to come. ושמעתי שהיו אומרים v'shamati shehayu omrim and I heard that
they said, it's by the way it's interesting, again, notice it switched
to the idea of Torah knowledge. Because before when it was תחתונים
למעלה, tachtonim l'ma'ala, and it's not talking about the rabbinic class, so
who are the תחתונים tachtonim that aren't getting respect? It probably refers
to אנשי מעשה, anshei ma'aseh, צדיקים, tzaddikkim, חסידים, chasidim, and nevertheless, it
then shifts back to the rabbinic concerns and mentions the idea of
תלמודו בידו talmudo b'yado as a particular thing that is given weight
and significance. ושמעתי שהיו אומרים v'shamati shehayu omrim and I also heard
that they said, הרוגי מלכות, harugei malchut, those that have been martyred,
killed by the Roman government,
martyred for their faith, אין אדם יכול לעמוד במחיצתם. ein adam yachol
la'amod bimchitzatam. Those are at the highest מדריגה. madrega. Nobody else can
stand in their section. So מאן נינהו? man ninhu? And who are
these people? So
אילימא רבי עקיבא וחביריו, eileima Rabbi Akiva v'chaverav, if you tell me
it's Rabbi Akiva and his colleagues, the great sages that were persecuted
and martyred in the Herodian persecutions. So משום הרוגי מלכות ותו לא?
mishum harugei malchut v'su lo? What? They only get their status because
of הרוגי מלכות? harugei malchut? Rabbi Akiva would get the highest status
because of his being a Torah sage. So again you get this
ongoing dynamics between giving recognition to those that are true righteous and
deserve עולם הבא olam haba on a high level because of things
they do outside of the world of Torah, because of their deeds
and because they martyred themselves, and not to forget of course the
tremendous status that is afforded to תלמידי חכמים. talmidei chachamim. So even
in this section of הרוגי מלכות harugei malchut that they, if it
was Rabbi Akiva, he'd get that status without being הרוגי מלכות. harugei
malchut.
I understand, but that's the whole point. The גמרא Gemara is not
saying that. It could have said yes, it's Rabbi Akiva. But if
it weren't that he were הרוגי מלכות, harugei malchut, it would be
others that would be במחיצתם. bimchitzatam. The גמרא Gemara doesn't say that.
So that's my point, that the גמרא Gemara is, while the one
hand giving focusing on those that are not sort of given recognition
and status and not of the rabbinic class, but are צדיקים tzaddikkim
and חסידים chasidim and so on, and saying that they get they
are עליונים elyonim in עולם הבא, olam haba, it's sort of constantly
also having this counterpoint to say, yes, but let's not forget about
the tremendous status that the תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim get.
You get the sense that the תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim is kind
of standing outside of this looking in as observers. Like we know
who we are, we're okay with that because same as with the
עמי הארץ, Am Ha'aretzs, it's like interesting. עולם הפוך, Olam Hafuch, you
know, like we're okay where we are, and they say that explicitly,
but we look at the rest of society and we see, you
know, these different things going.
Interesting, interesting.
So yes, is there Talmudic criticism of רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva short-sighted
political, you know? I mean he caused the death of a lot
of people.
Yeah,
I don't know.
In other words, it seems
like רבי יוחנן
בן זכאי,
Rabbi
Yochanan ben Zakkai, right?
Was the opposite.
Right, I mean you have the stories about רבי יוחנן בן זכאי
Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai and about those types of things, and can
you translate that to the רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva issues? I don't
know if there's a גמרא Gemara that really deals with רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva at from the sort of political through the political lens.
Not sure. All right, so it says, okay, so it can't be
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, אלא הרוגי לוד. Ella Harugei Lod. Those that
were killed in לוד. Lod. What's the story there? So there's a
גמרא Gemara story that there was a time when the government wanted
to sort of like hold the entire city of לוד Lod accountable
for the death of someone, and two people were willing to accept
to sort of take the blame and save the entire city from
being wiped out. You have there been stories like that in Jewish
history, sadly. So anyway, those two people that were willing to do
that, that's such a מדרגה madrega nobody can stand in their מחיצתם.
mechitzatam. Even if we're talking about the
average person let's say, that was, you know, accused whatever, like, for
their faith or something?
Yeah, so that's interesting too. Right, why
doesn't, right, exactly, why didn't it just say any person who was
willing to give up their life rather than renounce their faith? Why
did it have to specifically talk about like, you know, of like
people that were really, if you almost excuse the term, like celebrities,
people that were really outstanding in that regard? Maybe it's because of
the phrase of אין אדם יכול לעמוד במחיצתם, Ein adam yachol la'amod
bimechitzatam, it was understood that we're talking about a very specific subset.
But it's true, it could have made it much more broad.
They might not have considered Jewish experience generally to be one of
tragedy and martyrdom all the time. They might have even seen that
Jewish life
was—right, but if it says הרוגי מלכות, Harugei Malchut, right? Why do
you need to clarify? It's obvious who הרוגי מלכות Harugei Malchut is,
whoever has been martyred for their faith.
There might not have been that many examples.
But there were! I mean there were in the—I mean we know
there were, right? There were in the time of the חשמונאים, Chashmonaim,
there were in the time, I mean there were always.
It sort of leads me to say that they're kind of standing
outside of the—of society and looking in and commenting on it.
Because the normal הרוגי מלכות Harugei Malchut are like maybe more among
them and they're sort of
ourselves of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, or
we're looking at things that are more at arm's length from us.
That's a good point as well, going back to that other point,
that we're sort of looking at things that are arm's length from
our experience. Okay, ביום ההוא יהיה על מצלות הסוס קודש לה'. Bayom
hahu yihiyeh al metzilot hasus kodesh l'Hashem. On that day they will
put on the מצלות הסוס, metzilot hasus, which probably means like the
ornamentation or something, the words קודש לה'. kodesh l'Hashem. So what's this
מצלות הסוס? metzilot hasus? מאי מצלות הסוס? Mai metzilot hasus? אמר רבי
יהושע בן לוי, Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, עתיד הקדוש ברוך הוא
להוסיף על ירושלים, atid HaKadosh Baruch Hu lehosif al Yerushalayim, and רש''י
Rashi says this is why we're having this אגדתא, agadata, God will
eventually add on ירושלים, Yerushalayim, meaning the city of ירושלים Yerushalayim will
be—will grow, עד שהסוס רץ ומציל. ad shehasus ratz umatzil. So far
that an—that a horse can run, now מציל matzil you might say
means save, but רש''י Rashi says it means from the word צל,
tzel, and that the shade—it will still cast its shade, meaning the
half of a day, because by noon it's no longer casting its
shade. So anyway, the city will be so huge that it'll be
as big as the distance that a horse can run in—in six
hours, in half a day. So I actually was going to, I
didn't get a chance, I was going to though take a look
and find out how far that is and compare it to the
actual size of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, because, you know, I mean in the
time of the גמרא Gemara that was like, that was like, you
know, this fantastical to think of a city that size. Right, but
it's probably, I mean who knows, ירושלים Yerushalayim nowadays might actually be
close to that size. How big is ירושלים? Yerushalayim? Anybody knows in
terms of just
like—like miles across?
Not that big. Be six—I mean six hours of
a horse running, it's probably a good like, right, thirty miles or
more, sixty miles, something like that. Yeah, so—so okay, that's true. ירושלים
Yerushalayim isn't that big. It would certainly be enormously bigger than it
was in the time of the גמרא. Gemara. Anyway,
okay, רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, כל מצילות שתולים לסוס בין
עיניו, kol metzilot shetola'im lasus bein einav, any types of like ornaments,
this probably is closer to the פשט pshat that you hang between
like, you know, sometimes you see in these horses they have like,
you know, things like, you know, beads or whatever going down between
their eyes, so all the types of ornaments that they would hang
for on a horse between its eyes יהיה קודש לה', yihiyeh kodesh
l'Hashem, will be sanctified to God, everybody will sanctify it to
the Temple. Yes, all the stuff that people put on their horses
for ornaments will be sanctified that day to the Temple. רבי יוחנן
אמר, Rabbi Yochanan amar, כל ביזה שבוזין ישראל עד שהסוס רץ ומציל,
kol biza shebozin Yisrael ad shehasus ratz umatzil, all of the booty
that Israel, you know, takes in, captures for half of the day,
the time it takes a horse, you know, for the time that
a horse runs and casts its shade, so half of—half of a
day, in the war—so all the booty they capture in that war,
presumably the war of גוג ומגוג. Gog u'Magog. יהיה קודש להשם, yehiye
kodesh l'Hashem, they will sanctify to God. Okay, so בשלמא למאן דאמר
כל ביזה שבזו ישראל, bishlama le-man d'amar kol biza shebazu Yisrael, if
it's talking about giving all this booty to God and to the
temple, היינו דכתיב haynu d'chtiv that's the end of the פסוק pasuk
והיה הסירות בבית השם v'haya hasirot b'veit Hashem and it will be
that even the pots in the בית השם Beit Hashem will be
כמזרקים לפני המזבח k'mizrakim lifnei hamizbeach like the special vessels for throwing
the blood by the מזבח. mizbeach. What does that mean? It means
the same way those vessels are made out of gold and pure
gold, the ones used in the מזבח, mizbeach, so even your chamber
pots,
even your normal pots will be made out of gold. So that
fits in because we're talking about having all of this tremendous wealth.
So the following פסוק pasuk connects. אלא למאן דאמר בהנך תרתי, ela
le-man d'amar behanech tartei, but if the other two explanations, either talking
about the size of ירושלים Yerushalayim or talking about donating the jewelry
from the horses, jewelry from horses is not going to be enormous
wealth. So מאי והיה הסירות בבית השם? mai v'haya hasirot b'veit Hashem?
So how does the next פסוק pasuk follow up
from that previous פסוק? pasuk? מילתא אחריתי קאמר. milta achrita ka'amar. Fine,
it's a separate point. It's not a continuation of the previous point,
it's an additional point. דמיתעתרי ישראל ומתנדבי ומייתי d'mit'atrey Yisrael u-mitnadvey u-maytey
that yes, another point will be that there will be tremendous donations
and Israel will be very rich and they'll donate and you'll have
even gold pots. Okay. בשלמא למאן דאמר ביזה, bishlama le-man d'amar biza,
according to the explanation that it's talking about the booty, so היינו
דכתיב haynu d'chtiv that's what's meant ולא יהיה כנעני עוד בבית השם
צבאות v'lo yihye Kna'ani od b'veit Hashem Tzeva'ot that there will no
longer be a כנעני Kna'ani in the house of God. Why? Because
כנעני Kna'ani here is understood to mean a trader. We will see
why that means not traitor, trader,
somebody, so it means that we'll have so much wealth that we
won't have to anymore engage in like a type of a commerce,
the whole idea like you now go to ירושלים Yerushalayim and you
see all those booths and whatnot right around that were around the
בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So they would have to, the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash would be engaged in a certain amount of commerce and
transactions even at the time for people to bring their קרבנות. korbanot.
None of that will be necessary. And if we know about how
Jesus threw out
the money changers,
right, there was a lot of transactional stuff going on around the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash which was not necessarily seen as always fully
appropriate. So this is being read as it'll be so much wealth
that that will be unnecessary and none of that will take place
in the environs of the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
כנעני Kna'ani means a trader in אשת חיל, Eshet Chayil, that's the
פשט pshat in אשת חיל. Eshet Chayil.
Yeah, well we're going to get to אשת חיל Eshet Chayil in
a minute, but okay yes, right exactly, like the word כנעני Kna'ani
in אשת חיל Eshet Chayil sometimes interpreted that way. Yes. So that
we understand. אלא למאן דאמר בהנך תרתי, ela le-man d'amar behanech tartei,
but if you say it's these other things which aren't emphasizing enormous
wealth, מאי ולא יהיה כנעני? mai v'lo yihye Kna'ani? So אמר רבי
ירמיה אין כאן עני. amar Rabbi Yirmeya ein kan ani. Okay, which
I don't exactly get how that solves the problem. So it doesn't
mean there won't be traders, it'll mean that there won't be poor
people. Either way though, it's saying that they'll be wealthy, so I
don't get
why it was such a question and how changing the word of
כנעני Kna'ani answers it. Anyway, so the
גמרא Gemara says אין כאן עני. ein kan ani. וכנעני מנלן דאיקרי
תגר? v'Kna'ani minalan d'ikrei tager? How do you know that a כנעני
Kna'ani is called a trader or a trader is called a כנעני?
Kna'ani? דכתיב d'chtiv because the verse says וירא שם יהודה בת איש
כנעני. vayar sham Yehuda bat ish Kna'ani. יהודה Yehuda saw there the
daughter of a כנעני Kna'ani man, right,
ושמו שוע, u-shmo Shua, ויקחה ויבא אליה, vayikacheha vayavo eleiha, right? So
he married this כנעני Kna'ani woman or the daughter of a כנעני
Kna'ani man. So מאי כנעני? mai Kna'ani? What does the word כנעני
Kna'ani mean? אילימא כנעני ממש, ilima Kna'ani mamash, if you say literally
a כנעני, Kna'ani, אפשר? efshar? Is it possible that אברהם Avraham came
and he told יצחק, Yitzchak, right, or he told actually his servant,
I don't want my son marrying anybody
from who's born in this land? וביצחק והזהיר את יעקב u-v'Yitzchak v'hizhir
et Ya'akov and יצחק Yitzchak came and he said to יעקב, Ya'akov,
he says אל תקח אשה מבנות כנען, al tikach isha mibnot Kna'an,
קום לך פדנה ארם, kum lech Padana Aram, right, they're all sending
them away and saying don't marry any כנענית? Kna'anit? ויהודה אזיל ונסיב
v'Yehuda azil v'nasiv and יהודה Yehuda is going to go and marry
a כנעני Kna'ani woman? I understand, but the גמרא Gemara can't believe
it. אלא אמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש בת גברא תגרא. ela amar
Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish bat gavra tagra. Oh, it must mean not
literally
the daughter of a כנעני Kna'ani man, it must mean the daughter
of a trader. דכתיב d'chtiv now כנען בידו מאזני מרמה Kna'an beyado
mozney mirma and from a פסוק pasuk which now might be referring
to the כנעני Kna'ani nation, but here is again seeming to refer
to traders, they have in their
hands
balances of deceit. So you see it's talking about people that use
balances, so who are the people that weigh things with balances? Obviously
they are traders. ואיבעית אימא מהכא, v'iba'it eima mehacha, and if you
want from here,
אשר סוחריה שרים כנעניה נכבדי ארץ. asher sochareha sarim Kna'aneha nichbadai aretz.
That's actually a very good proof because it's talking not about a
nation, it's talking about the members of a nation and its כנענים,
Kna'anim, so presumably it's understood to parallel סוחריה, sochareha, its merchants, its
traders are those that
are of the land.
I
mean it's a,
you know, it's a question about how that nation was perceived at
the time and the types of associations that were given to that
people. So it could refer to still a people, but you know,
with the certain associations. Okay, so והיה
ה' למלך על כל הארץ, Vehaya Hashem L'melech Al Kol Ha'aretz, since
we're talking about the messianic time, God will be king over the
entire earth. ביום ההוא יהיה ה' אחד Bayom Hahu Yiheyeh Hashem Echad
that day God will be one ושמו אחד U'shmo Echad and his
name one. So the גמרא Gemara says אטו האידנא לאו אחד הוא,
Atu Ha'idna Lav Echad Hu, what do you mean? Is God not
one nowadays? God's always one. So אמר רבי אחא בר חנינא, Amar
Rabbi Acha Bar Chanina, so you could have obviously the simple explanation
could be, you know, he'll be understood to be one, he'll be
seen as one by everybody. But okay, so seeing this as a
theological statement, what does it mean that God will only be one
then and he's not one now? לא כעולם הזה עולם הבא, Lo
K'olam Hazeh Olam Haba, not like this world is the world to
come. העולם הזה על בשורות טובות אומר, Ha'olam Hazeh Al B'sorot Tovot
Omer, this world when good things happen you say ברוך הטוב והמטיב,
Baruch Hatov Ve'hametiv, blessed is God who does good. ועל בשורות רעות
אומר, Ve'al B'sorot Raot Omer, when bad things happen you say ברוך
דיין האמת, Baruch Dayan Ha'emet, blessed is the true judge. Meaning, you
recognize, you give blessing to God, but ultimately it's recognizing that it's
a bad thing that happened, at least from your perspective. לעולם הבא,
L'olam Haba, but in the world to come, כולו הטוב והמטיב. Kulo
Hatov Ve'hametiv. Nobody's going to have to make the ברכה Bracha of
דיין האמת. Dayan Ha'emet. It'll only be a world of good. So
God's שמו, Shmo, God will be אחד Echad in the way that
God will be only associated, you know, they won't give two different
ברכות Brachot to God. God will only be associated with the good.
Our experience of God and of God's, you know, sort of God's
presence in this world will only be the good of God and
never the stuff that is negative.
Presumably, yeah, I mean there are those beliefs in עולם הבא, Olam
Haba, you know, this debate,
I'm not going to get into the million debates about what happens
in עולם הבא. Olam Haba. Yes.
Why did they need to go with that? To me, I always
thought that verse is everybody's going to believe in God.
That's what I said before, there's a simple sense of the פשט,
Pshat, right?
But you know, some, and again, if you said that the problem
is is that the והיה ה' אחד Vehaya Hashem Echad doesn't mean
at our experiential level, it means in some objective theological sense. But
the answer is about our experiential level, right? It's not that God
will be different, it's that we'll only experience the goodness of God.
So if it's about our experience of it, right, so why can't
you just say everybody will recognize that God is one? I really
don't, I really don't know. Again, maybe this is something that's very
much from the Jewish perspective, you know, we're not even talking about
the non-Jews. But even from the Jewish perspective, there'll be some change
that God will be אחד Echad in a way that he's not
אחד Echad nowadays. So, you know, maybe that's what's bothering the גמרא.
Gemara. Okay, so let's look at the end of the פסוק. Pasuk.
Okay, so ושמו
אחד, U'shmo Echad, מאי
אחד? Mai Echad? What do you mean God's name will be one?
אטו האידנא לאו שמו אחד הוא? Atu Ha'idna Lav Shmo Echad Hu?
And again, you could say yeah, you know, like the people have
different names for God, right? You know, so we could say that
everybody will have a unified and the same call God by the
same name, which is not just a question of name but means
a unified belief. But again, the גמרא Gemara is not focusing on
the, you know, perspective of the larger world. Presumably it's focusing on
the Jewish perspective. So what does it mean that his name will
become one? So אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman Bar
Yitzchak, לא כעולם הזה עולם הבא. Lo K'olam Hazeh Olam Haba. It's
not like this world the world to come. העולם הזה נכתב ביו"ד
ה"א, Ha'olam Hazeh Nichtav B'yod Heh, in this world God's name is
written in יו"ד ה"א, Yod Heh, ונקרא באל"ף דל"ת, Ve'nikra B'aleph Dalet,
but we don't read it the way it's written. We read it
as אדנות. Adnut. So therefore God's name as it were is two.
It's pronounced in a different way than it's written, so there's some
non-unity there. אבל לעולם הבא כולו אחד. Aval L'olam Haba Kulo Echad.
In the next world it'll all be unified. נכתב ביו"ד ה"א ונקרא
ביו"ד ה"א. Nichtav B'yod Heh Ve'nikra B'yod Heh. It'll be written with
יו"ד ה"א Yod Heh and it'll be read with יו"ד ה"א. Yod
Heh. So we'll actually give God God's proper name and that will
you know, and that again will be this sort of direct experience
of God that there's none of these, if you would, like מחיצות,
Mechitzot, these curtains in which we have to refer to God in
some different name because of this distance
between us and a world of perfection.
וסבר רבא למידרשיה בפירקא. Ve'savar Rava L'midrashei B'pirka. Now רבא Rava thought,
hey, you know what? I'm going to teach people what the real
pronunciation of God's יו"ד ה"א Yod Heh name is. And he was
going to teach it,
you know,
at the in the public
forum. אמר ליה ההוא סבא, Amar Lei Hahu Saba, so a certain
old person said to him, it's funny like some old guy in
the audience,
לעלם כתיב. Le'alem Ktiv.
It's written זה שמי לעולם, Zeh Shmi L'olam, forever,
but it's written without the ו. Vav. And you could read it
in the language of העלם He'elem like לעלם. Le'alem. How would you
pronounce it? לעלם? Le'alem? Yeah. So לעלם Le'alem which means to cover
up and to hide. רב אבינא רמי. Rav Avina Rami. So therefore
we shouldn't even be... telling people what it is nowadays. Not only
do we not pronounce it, but maybe almost in a way it's
something that's not even to be spoken about, you know, and it
really is, that'll be God's name in עולם הבא. Olam HaBa. You
know, when we, but nowadays we live with a like, you know,
with it in somehow, you know, in a through, through a, you
know, through a filter. רבי אבינא רמי. Rabbi Avina rami. כתיב Ktiv
one verse says זה שמי לעולם ze shemi le'olam or the same
verse says וזה זכרי לדור דור. veze zichri ledor dor. So which
is it? Meaning, is it, it's one thing. What do you mean
this is my name and this is how I'm remembered? Presumably how
my name is how I'm remembered. So, what are the two halves
of the פסוק pasuk doing? So, אמר קדוש ברוך הוא Amar Kadosh
Baruch Hu לא כשאני נכתב אני נקרא. lo k'she'ani nichtav ani nikra.
Not the way my name is written, although it's, it's actually this
is a even a more almost anthropomorphic, it's not even not the
way my name is written. Not the way I am written אני
נקרא ani nikra am I read. נכתב אני ביוד הי. nichtav ani
be'yud he. I'm written with יוד הי. yud he. So that's זה
שמי. ze shemi. So my true name is זה שמי ze shemi
and also לעולם le'olam is also לעלם, le'alem, my true name is
to be hidden. וזה זכרי, veze zichri, the way I'm remembered and
evoked is not by my true name but with this other name.
ונקרא אני באלף דלד venikra ani be'alef daled and I am read
with the אלף דלד. alef daled. So again the sense of an
imperfection of this world but almost an imperfection in the sense of
how we're able to experience God. So we experience also, you know,
the bad and as opposed to experiencing God just as a God
of good, and we also experience God in a less full way
so even the name that we use is not somehow does not
truly reflect the true essence of God. Okay, wow, that was pretty
powerful. הדרן עלך אלו עוברין Hadran alach eilu overin and that is
the end of the third פרק perek which as I said is
the first three פרקים prakim devoted to the topic of חמץ. chametz.
And now we start the fourth פרק perek which somewhat stands on
its own. It's a פרק perek that deals a lot with מנהגים,
minhagim, different מנהגים minhagim and the basis for the idea of מנהג
minhag as a binding concept. And we start with the מנהג minhag
of ערב פסח. Erev Pesach. So let's take a look. מקום שנהגו
לעשות מלאכה בערבי פסחים עד חצות עושים. Makom shenahagu la'asot melacha be'arvei
pesachim ad chatzot osim. So clearly what's implicit in this משנה mishna
is they would not do מלאכה melacha from midday on. Okay, they'd
be bringing the קרבן פסח, korban pesach, all getting ready, all these
things. But how about until noon? Could you do מלאכה melacha or
not? That was based on different מנהגים. minhagim. So the place where
they allowed one to
do מלאכת הרשות melachat ha'reshut clearly. What? מלאכת הרשות melachat ha'reshut what
there's you have to burn your חמץ chametz is also...
Yeah, yeah, yeah. No, yeah, yeah, yeah. We're not talking about like,
you know, right. מלאכה melacha means like... Yeah, yeah, yeah. We're not
talking about a formal category of מלאכה. melacha. At least presumably not,
presumably we're talking about like, you know, going to work. Okay. So,
you know, being engaged, you know, in, in, professionally or in like,
you know, time-consuming labor.
אבל לא בעניינא דיומא. aval lo be'inyana deyoma.
Right. Exactly. Exactly. Meaning taking off from work and devoting yourself או
אולי איסור, o ulai issur, it's the same... Exactly. Are you taking
off from work and devoting yourself to getting ready for פסח? Pesach?
Okay, if you look at the first רש״י, Rashi, okay, so we'll
just read the next lines. So if you have the מנהג minhag
to allow, the place where people do מלאכה melacha until חצות, chatzot,
fine. מקום שנהגו שלא לעשות אין עושים. Makom shenahagu shelo la'asot ein
osim. Place where they don't do, then you don't do. It's this,
so besides by the way
implicitly recognizing the binding nature of מנהגים, minhagim, which is an important
question, since when do מנהגים minhagim become binding? It's also very powerfully
also recognizing a type of אלו ואלו, eilu ve'eilu, the ability to
tolerate multiple different practices and not have to say this one is
right and this one is wrong and we have to be completely
uniform. Now what's the שלא לעשות, shelo la'asot, why not? So רש״י
Rashi says, the first רש״י Rashi here, two lines on the bottom,
כדי שלא יהא טרוד במלאכה וישכח. kedei shelo yehei tarud bemelacha veyishkach.
What? And you'll forget the things you have to do. What are
the things you have to do on פסח? Pesach? ביעור חמץ, biur
chametz,
getting rid of your חמץ. chametz. שחיטת הפסח, shechitat hapesach, slaughtering your
פסח pesach which is after חצות, chatzot, but okay. ותיקון מצה, vetikkun
matzah, and making the מצות matzot for ליל סדר. leil seder. Okay,
which is interesting because, and now why do you have to do
all that? דמצווה לטרוח מבעוד יום כדי להסב מהר. demitzvah litro'ach mibe'od
yom kedei lehaseiv maher. So you see even in their days, they
want everybody wanted to start the סדר seder early. Okay, so you
have to get everything ready before it becomes night so that you
can start the סדר seder as soon as possible. Right? חלוקת מצה
בליל פסחים בשביל תינוקות שלא ישנו. chalukat matzah be'leil pesachim bishvil tinokot
shelo yishanu.
So the problem about the kids falling asleep was a practice way
back that went way back then. So you've got to do all
the stuff and you've got to, got to get it ready so
that you can start the סדר seder as soon as possible. Okay,
so if that's your practice even from the morning, then that's the
practice. Now, ההולך ממקום שעושים למקום שאין עושים או ממקום שאין עושים
למקום שעושים. Hahoilech mimakom she'osim lemakom she'ein osim o mimakom she'ein osim
lemakom she'osim.
Let's say you come from one place and you're visiting the other
place and it's ערב פסח, Erev Pesach, what do you do? נותנים
עליו חומרי מקום שיצא משם וחומרי מקום שהלך לשם. notnin alav chumrei
makom sheyatza misham vechumrei makom shehalach lesham. So this is, right, this
is the famous issue which comes up second day of יום טוב,
Yom Tov, we'll talk about that. Anyway, you give him the stringencies
of where he left and where he's going, which means he doesn't
do מלאכה. melacha. You get the worst of both worlds. You have
to on the one hand respect where you came from, so if
they're more stringent you have to not do it מלאכה, melacha, and
you have to respect where you are, which is if the place
you're in doesn't do מלאכה, melacha, you don't do מלאכה. melacha. ואל
ישנה אדם מפני המחלוקת. ve'al yishaneh adam mipnei hamachloket. מחלוקת. machloket. And
you should not do different from what other people are doing because
of it'll lead to, it'll lead to controversy. So on the one
hand,
respecting different practice, but that's very nice, different practices in different places.
If you have different practices in the same place, that could lead
to more debate, and that's where you actually should more try to
respect the conventions for the sake of שלום. shalom. So it's interesting.
Now, right. So the problem of course that Michael realizes is that
if you came from a place that doesn't do מלאכה melacha to
a place that does, then you are being משנה meshaneh ממנהג
המקום.
miminhag
hamakom. Alright, so the גמרא Gemara will discuss that. That that's not
as obvious that you're doing something different just because you're lounging around
watching TV. But if nobody is doing מלאכה melacha and you're out
there and you're working and plowing the field, then you're obviously doing
something different. Okay, but I also think as I said conceptually it's
interesting because on the one hand it embraces the diversity, but it
realizes there's times for diversity and then there's also times
for more uniform practice, for שלום shalom and to try to everybody
keeping to a certain convention. So in your own place it's fine,
but if it's together it could lead to debate. Now nowadays of
course there's issues about us living in more heterogeneous communities. You know,
so like questions about wearing תפילין tefillin on
חול המועד Chol HaMoed used to be so contentious. And nowadays you
go into שולס shuls and you'll see like half the people are
wearing תפילין tefillin and half the people aren't. So if you live
in a community that by nature is heterogeneous, the issue of uniformity
might be less. But in those days certainly the communities were much
more uniform. Okay. כיוצא בו, keyotzei bo, similarly, המוליך פירות שביעית ממקום
שכלו למקום שלא כלו. hamolich peirot shevi'it mimakom shekalu lemakom shelo kalu.
If you are, now the שמיטה Shemita produce you have to, you
can no longer eat it and you have to destroy it once
it is no longer available out in the field to the animals.
Like you know everything's been taken in the house, there's nothing that's
left on the trees, left in the yards, there's nothing for the
animals. You have to destroy then what you have in your house.
But let's say you took had your apples and where you were
they were the period of destroying them and you went to a
place where there were still apples on the tree or vice versa.
So you went ממקום שכלו למקום שלא כלו, mimakom shekalu lemakom shelo
kalu, a place where they had no were no longer available out
in the fields to a place where they were still available. או
ממקום שלא כלו למקום שכלו. o mimakom shelo kalu lemakom shekalu. So
in both cases חייב לבער. chayav leva'er. Again, you give the stringencies
of the place either you left or you're going to and therefore
you have to destroy them because in one of those places you
have to destroy them. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, Rabbi Yehuda
says, צא והבא לך אף אתה, tzei vehavei lecha af ata, go
out and bring even you. So what the heck does that mean?
So the גמרא Gemara will figure that out.
Okay.
Maybe. Okay, let's take a look. We'll see in the גמרא Gemara
what that means. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
If you come from a place where they don't the מנהג minhag
is not to do מלאכה melacha and you go to a place
where the מנהג minhag is to do מלאכה. melacha.
Right, to allow people to do מלאכה. melacha. To allow people. It
doesn't require, right?
So could you do מלאכה melacha according to this in that place?
No. So that's the point. You keep the stringencies of the place
you came from.
Even though it's different.
And that's a question. That's not being uniform. But again, Michael anticipate
what the גמרא Gemara is going to say, which is to לא
תתגודדו. lo titgodedu. Exactly. The מנהג minhag of this place is to
allow people to do מלאכה, melacha, not to require people to do
מלאכה. melacha. So by you not doing מלאכה, melacha, you're not going
against the practice of the place. So that actually can work. But
there would be times like the תפילין tefillin example where you can't,
you know, do both maintain the conventions of this place and respect
where you came from and it'll be an obvious violation either way.
You know, either you'll have so it's not always possible to keep
the חומרות chumrot of both and keep the sense of a uniform
practice, a uniform with the place that you're at. Okay, let's take
a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. מאי איריא ערבי פסחים? mai irya arvei pesachim? Now why
are we talking about ערב פסח? erev pesach? It's a funny question
because we're talking about ערב פסח erev pesach because it applies no,
but besides that, but the point meaning the גמרא's Gemara going to
say in by other cases you also can't do מלאכה melacha by
midday. But that's fine, we're not emphasizing the noon forward, we're emphasizing
the first half of the day. But somehow the גמרא's Gemara bothered
with the idea
that it seems like we're emphasizing I don't I can't even really
understand the question. But somehow the גמרא Gemara seems that this seems
like you're trying to say a חידוש chiddush that from פסח pesach
that there's a חידוש chiddush that you can't do מלאכה melacha from
midday on according to everyone. That's not such a חידוש, chiddush, it's
true on other ערב יום טוב erev yom tov as well.
מאי איריא ערבי פסחים אפילו ערבי שבתות וערבי ימים טובים נמי? mai
irya arvei pesachim afilu arvei shabbatot v'arvei yamim tovim nami? Even a
normal ערב שבת, erev shabbat, ערב יום טוב erev yom tov you
can't do מלאכה melacha from midday on. דתניא, detanya, we'll talk about
it, we taught in a ברייתא: braita: העושה מלאכה בערבי שבתות וימים
טובים מן המנחה ולמעלה. ha'oseh melacha b'arvei shabbatot v'yamim tovim min hamincha
ulema'lah. If somebody does מלאכה melacha on ערב שבת erev shabbat from
מנחה mincha onwards. Now anyway what's
מנחה? mincha? It's מנחה גדולה, mincha gedola, right, or מנחה קטנה? mincha
ktana? רש"י Rashi says it means מנחה קטנה, mincha ktana, so already
we're only talking about 3:30 in the day, we're not talking about
the whole afternoon. So אינו רואה סימן ברכה. eino ro'eh siman bracha.
You don't see, you won't there won't be a blessing in your
work. So the גמרא Gemara says לעולם התם אינו רואה סימן ברכה
לעולם. l'olam hatam eino ro'eh siman bracha l'olam. You'll never see a
ברכה bracha in presumably of the work that you've done, not in
any work you'll do in the future. Anyway, התם מן המנחה ולמעלה
הוא דאסור. hatam min hamincha ulema'lah hu de'asur. No, there it's only
forbidden מנחה mincha onwards, which again according to רש"י Rashi means... 3:30
onwards. סמוך למנחה לא, samuch lemincha lo, next to מנחה mincha not,
meaning the period, again you could read that the half hour because
מנחה mincha time, מנחה גדולה mincha gedola is 12:30. So then we're
only debating 12 or 12:30, but רש״י Rashi says the difference is
3:30 versus noon. Okay, הכא מחצות, hacha mechatzot, here already it's noon,
so that's a huge difference. אי נמי, i nami, or another difference,
התם סימן ברכה הוא דלא חזי, hatam siman beracha hu delo chazi,
there it's just that your work isn't blessed. אבל שמותי לא משמתינן
ליה, aval shamutei lo meshamtinan lei, we wouldn't like put him in
נידוי nidui or in חרם, cherem, which means you didn't technically violate
anything. Technically you're allowed, you just have to be able to deal
with the fact that there won't be a ברכה beracha in your
work, but technically it's allowed.
הכא, hacha, the same, the same מחלוקת machloket as where? Beginning of
שבת, Shabbat, the same
why is it confined to this?
The beginning of ערב פסחים erev Pesachim about eating ערב פסח. erev
Pesach. Yeah, and this is about doing מלאכה melacha ערב פסח, erev
Pesach, but Dov is correct, there'll be a parallel discussion in a
at 10, right, in the 10th פרק perek about eating ערב פסח
erev Pesach versus eating ערב שבת. erev Shabbat. Okay, this is about
doing work. So הכא שמותי נמי משמתינן ליה. hacha shamutei nami meshamtinan
lei. Here we'd be prepared to put him into חרם, cherem, which
means here he's actually violating. It's not just that you don't see
a סימן ברכה. siman beracha. So there is a difference. By the
way,
even within that context of it's סימן ברכה siman beracha and it's
only from 3:30, even so, like how many people do we know
that say, oh my god, like you can't do any מלאכה melacha
from 3:30 on or you won't see a סימן ברכה? siman beracha?
So if you take a look at תוספות, Tosafot, no, no, you
won't get excommunicated, that's for ערב פסח, erev Pesach, but the point
is you won't see a סימן ברכה. siman beracha. Anyway, no, no,
ערב, erev, fine, ערב פסח, erev Pesach, that's a good point too.
How many people, I wasn't even thinking about that, but that's true
also. How many people take the איסור מלאכה issur melacha ערב פסח
erev Pesach as seriously as they need to? But every ערב שבת,
erev Shabbat, do people say three, oh it's 3:30, I have to
whatever? So take a look at תוספות, Tosafot, עושה מלאכה במוצאי, oseh
melacha bemotzaei, oh, actually that's במוצאי שבת, bemotzaei Shabbat, so תוספות Tosafot
plays it down a little by מוצאי שבת. motzaei Shabbat. But anyway,
so that's a real issue. You know, הרב סולובייצ׳יק HaRav Soloveitchik says,
said in one writing, I'm forgetting which but it's some article, he
said, you know, he said, ברוך השם, Baruch Hashem, I come to
America and I see that, you know, you have this very serious
observant community, people that are really, you know, מקפיד, makpid, שומר שבת
shomer Shabbat Jews. He says, but what you don't have is שומר
ערב שבת shomer erev Shabbat Jews. You know, the idea of devoting
ערב שבת erev Shabbat to preparing for שבת, Shabbat, he says you
don't see that in America. I actually know somebody here in the
Riverdale community that said after she read that, she started taking off
work on Fridays so she could spend Fridays just getting ready for
שבת. Shabbat. And so, and it's really a very profound thing about,
well, you know, the idea of spending the time in and, you
know, the experience of something is so connected to the preparation and,
you know, and the buildup that we have for it beforehand.
But למעשה, lema'aseh, you know, those of us that like work, you
know, I can't be leaving 3:30 in the.
I understand, it's not always people's options. How many people have that
degree of latitude over their work and over their job and so
on? Look, the גמרא Gemara in the end says in the end
it's not אסור, assur, it's just סימן ברכה siman beracha and according
to רש״י Rashi it's only from 3:30, but again people are probably,
I think are completely oblivious of this. I mean they know they
gotta come home in time and they gotta schedule themselves so that
they're not מחלל שבת, mechalel Shabbat, but there's this idea I think
people are oblivious. What about ערב פסח? erev Pesach? People tend to
be pretty oblivious.
All right, is that, is that's sort of going to be kind
of really hefty?
That's, I mean we can, I'll see if I can find any
like פוסקים poskim that talk about, you know, mitigating that at all,
but that's certainly the פסק, psak, yeah.
I think, well, it was just one thing is the issue to
me it seems like if everyone in the family is just rushing
in last minute and you just buy takeout
as opposed to someone in the home starting to take time.
Yeah, but what I don't understand, but you're thinking but in the
time of חז״ל Chazal the woman was always in the house and
they're still saying אסור assur to do מלאכה. melacha.
You just have חכמים chachamim who are blessed for actually preparing the
food, chopping the fish.
Yeah, right, getting involved, but that's a little, but they're doing 5%
of the work, their wives are still doing 95%.
Okay, but what I was going to ask is this לשון lashon
of חומרא? chumra? Yes.
Specifically a part of the vocabulary of מנהג? minhag? In other words,
is חומרא chumra in the גמרא Gemara also equally a language of
הלכה halacha and חיוב chiyuv or is it in the lexicon of
הלכה halacha is חומרא? chumra?
Well, where do you see the language of חומרא? chumra? You mean
the
idea חומרי מקום chumrei makom שיצא משם. sheyatza misham.
In other words, I'm wondering if the technical terminology of חומרא chumra
is always תלמודית Talmudit associated with מנהג minhag and not with חיוב.
chiyuv. Right, I mean,
I'd have to check. My gut sense is is that you do
have חומרא chumra very also in areas where it's like there's a
debate and are you adopting the more מחמיר machmir position? Look, take
a look at the issue we had just a few days ago
where it says that there's a contradiction between right, the whole thing
about remember the בצק batzek and the עריבה ariva and is it
filling the hole whatever and there was two contradictions and one opinion
said get rid of the חמירתא chamirta מפני קליתא, mipnei kalita, get
rid of the קליתא kalita מפני חמירתא, mipnei chamirta, reject the more
lenient ברייתא braita in favor of the more strict ברייתא, braita, you
know? So the idea that identifying, how about, you know, חומרי בית
שמאי קולי בית הלל, chumrei Beit Shammai kulei Beit Hillel, identifying positions.
as חומרות, chumros, you know, is pervasive in halachic debate. Yeah. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
גופא. Gufa. העושה מלאכה בערבי שבתות ובערבי ימים טובים מן המנחה ולמעלה,
Haoseh melacha be'arvei shabbatos uve'arvei yamim tovim min hamincha ulemala, so if
one who does מלאכה melacha on ערב שבת Erev Shabbos ערב יום
טוב Erev Yom Tov from מנחה Mincha onwards, and now we're going
to add another thing, ובמוצאי שבת ובמוצאי יום טוב ובמוצאי יום הכיפורים,
u'veMotzei Shabbos u'veMotzei Yom Tov u'veMotzei Yom HaKippurim, and even if you
do it on the periods on מוצאי שבת Motzei Shabbos and יום
טוב Yom Tov and יום כיפורים, Yom Kippurim, ובכל מקום שיש נדנוד
עבירה, u'vechol makom sheyesh nidnud aveira, anytime that there would be a
concern of sin, meaning that because if you do מלאכה melacha too
early you would actually violate, so what would be cases of doing
מלאכה melacha that you might violate? לאתויי תענית ציבור, Le'asuyei ta'anis tzibur,
which is interesting. So there are some תענית ציבור ta'anis tzibors that
are done for rain that accompanying them is an איסור מלאכה. issur
melacha. The גר"א Gra changes the גירסא girsa to לאתויי תשעה באב
le'asuyei Tisha B'Av where there's also an idea of not doing מלאכה,
melacha, although there too it's, you know, if you do מלאכה melacha
on תשעה באב Tisha B'Av אינו רואה סימן ברכה, eino ro'eh siman
bracha, so maybe that's why it's נדנוד עבירה nidnud aveira not an
actual עבירה. aveira. אינו רואה סימן ברכה לעולם, Eino ro'eh siman bracha
le'olam, so you don't see a סימן ברכה. siman bracha. But what
gets added here is the מוצאי, Motzei, and the מוצאי Motzei you
see that the problem is not just the issue of time to
prepare, but it's also the idea of almost the concept of like
תוספת שבת tosefes Shabbos and תוספת יום טוב, tosefes Yom Tov, which
is to make sure that you don't end too early and you
don't violate. And that's if you look at the top little תוספות,
Tosafos, העושה מלאכה במוצאי שבתות, Haoseh melacha beMotzei Shabbatos, אומר ר"י דאיירי
בירושלמי דאיתא בירושלמי הכי, Omer Ri de'airy biYerushalmi de'isa biYerushalmi hachi, הני
נשי דנהיגי דלא למיעבד עבידתא באפוקי שבתא, hanni nashei denerigi delo lemievad
avidta be'appukei shabta, women that have the practice not to do מלאכה
melacha when שבת Shabbos on מוצאי שבת, Motzei Shabbos, לאו מנהגא lav
minhaga is not a legitimate מנהג. minhag. And by the way, that's
a theme we're going to start seeing about legitimate and not legitimate
מנהגים. minhagim. עד דתפני סדרא, Ad detifnei sidra, if they wait until
the סדרא sidra meaning the דאבנינג davening is over, then מנהגא minhaga
it's valid. פירשו שישלים התפילה Pirshu sheyashlim hatfilla מנהג כשר. minhag kosher.
ובהא נמי איירי הכא. Uv'ha nami airy hachi. So here it says
don't do it. It just means a tiny little time, you know,
don't cut it too close. Okay, but it's a different concern than
doing it on ערב שבת. Erev Shabbos.
You know, doing מלאכה melacha at 9:00 PM when שבת... Shabbos...
Exactly. Okay, let's get a little further. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. יש
זריז ונשכר ויש זריז ונפסד. Yesh zariz veniskar veyesh zariz venifsad. There's
somebody that is very זריז zariz diligent and gets is rewarded, and
those that are diligent and and loses out. יש שפל ונשכר ויש
שפל ונפסד. Yesh shafel veniskar veyesh shafel venifsad. There's somebody who's lazy
and is
rewarded and somebody who's lazy and loses out. זריז ונשכר, Zariz veniskar,
diligent in your work and you're rewarded, דעביד כולי שבתא ולא עביד
במעלי שבתא. de'avid kulei shabta velo avid bema'alei shabta. You work the
entire week and you take off on Friday. So you're you're rewarded
for your diligence, but you know that there's a limit and you
don't work on ערב שבת. Erev Shabbos. That's a זריז ונשכר. zariz
veniskar. זריז ונפסד, Zariz venifsad, then you could be diligent and lose
out, דעביד כולי שבתא ועביד במעלי שבתא. de'avid kulei shabta ve'avid bema'alei
shabta. You work hard the whole week including ערב שבת. Erev Shabbos.
In the end that's going to come back to bite you. Okay.
שפל ונשכר, Shafel veniskar, that's the next case. שפל ונשכר, Shafel veniskar,
somebody who is like lazy and rewarded, is דלא עביד כולי שבתא
ולא עביד במעלי שבתא. delo avid kulei shabta velo avid bema'alei shabta.
You don't work at all the week and you don't even work
on ערב שבת. Erev Shabbos. So you're נשכר niskar because at least
on Friday you're not working. It's like they say, you know, a
stopped clock is right is right twice a day. So if you
don't work at all, so on ערב שבת Erev Shabbos you succeed,
oh, excellent, you weren't working on ערב שבת. Erev Shabbos.
שפל ונפסד, Shafel venifsad, somebody who's lazy and loses out, דלא עביד
כולי שבתא ועביד במעלי שבתא. delo avid kulei shabta ve'avid bema'alei shabta.
The whole week you don't
work, but you work on Friday. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, הני נשי
דמחוזא, hanni nashei deMechuza, the women of מחוזא, Mechuza, אף על גב
דלא עבדן עבידתא במעלי שבתא משום מפנקותא, af al gav delo avdan
avidta bema'alei shabta mishum mafnekusa, even though they don't work on ערב
שבת Erev Shabbos because they're pampered, good word, because they're overly pampered,
רבא Rava was a big critic of the overly cosmopolitan and indulgent
ways of מחוזא. Mechuza. But even though they don't work, but here
he's going to be nice. So he has to get a little,
you know, critique in. They don't do it not out of any
religious motivation, they're just, you know, it's going to be שבת, Shabbos,
we might as well take Friday off.
דהא כל יומא נמי לא קא עבדן, Deha kol yoma nami lo
ka avdan, because look, anyway, they don't work the rest of the
week. So it's not taking even Friday off. It's just these so
pampered women that spend, you know, that don't work any day. So
אפילו הכי שפל ונשכר קרינן להו. afillu hachi shafel veniskar karinan lehu.
They are non-diligent in working but they are rewarded because at least
for Friday they get their reward for not working on Friday.
Regarding this, you know, not cutting it too close before or after
שבת, Shabbos, we should bear in mind that we're accustomed to having
timepieces that measure the tell us exactly now שבת Shabbos is over,
but that wasn't the case.
Exactly. And it was more visual and it was less precise. Absolutely.
Okay. רבא רמי. Rava ramy. רבא Rava shows a contradiction. כתיב, Kesiv,
the verse says כי גדול עד שמים חסדך, ki gadol ad shamayim
chasdecha, God your kindness is up to the heavens, וכתיב כי גדול
מעל שמים חסדך, u'kesiv ki gadol me'al shamayim chasdecha, even higher than
the heavens. הא כיצד? Ha keitzad? What's the, how do you reconcile?
כאן בעושים לשמה וכאן בעושים שלא לשמה. Kan be'osim lishma vekan be'osim
shelo lishma. If you do a מצוה לשמה, mitzvah lishma, then the
kindness you get from God goes above the heavens. If you do
it שלא לשמה, shelo lishma, it goes only up to the heavens.
So it's not as good, but it still is deserving of a
lot of reward. Tying into this idea of, you know, just because
you were taking off because You were lazy, but nevertheless, even if
you did it for the wrong reason, you'll still get rewarded. And
if you do it for the right reason, you'll get an even
bigger reward. Right, exactly, of course, the right reason's bigger. Like רב
יהודה *Rav Yehuda*, like רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* דאמר רב יהודה אמר
רב *d'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav* לעולם יעסוק אדם בתורה ומצות אף
על פי שלא לשמה Lishma. שמתוך שלא לשמה בא לשמה *Le'olam ya'asok
adam be-Torah u-mitzvot af al pi she-lo lishma she-mitoch she-lo lishma ba
lishma*: even do it for the not right reason, 'cause at least
then it'll lead to the right reason. Let's just read for a
few more minutes 'cause it goes very quick here. So if you
can stay for a few more minutes. תנו רבנן Tanu Rabanan: *Tanu
Rabbanan*: המצפה לשכר אשתו וריחיים אינו רואה סימן ברכה Siman Beracha לעולם
*ha-metzapeh li-sechar ishto ve-reichayim eino roeh siman beracha le-olam*. So if somebody
basically is hoping to get a, you know, get a big profit
from the work of his, from the, from the, from his, the
work of his wife or from a millstone, he will never really
see a good profit. Why? שכר אשתו *sechar ishto*, what does that
mean? מתקולתא *matkolta*. So רש״י *Rashi* says it means that she, like
a, like a, like a scale, a measuring scale, and she goes
out and she rents it out to people and it's just not
a very profitable enterprise. תוספות *Tosfot* says that it means the woman
is doing knitting and the problem is that she's doing her knitting
or, you know, out in the public and therefore she's exposing her
arms and so on, it's a problem. Who says she's knitting on
the? I don't know. ריחיים *reichayim*, and what does the millstone mean?
אגרתא *agarta*. That's if you're renting it, apparently that's not a very
profitable business. אבל עבדה ומזבנה *Aval avda u-mezavna*, but if you go
ahead and you work it or you sell and you sell, אשתבוחי
משתבח בה קרא *ishtabuchi mishtabach ba kera*. דכתיב *De-chtiv*: סדין עשתה ותמכר
*sadin asta va-timkor*.
So again, it actually quoting אשת חיל *Eshet Chayil*, right? דחגור נתנה
לכנעני *De-chagor natna la-Kena'ani*, right? Anyway, so anyway, so if she actually
goes ahead and she, and that fits into what תוספות *Tosfot* said
that before it went knitting, but the point is, this is about
if you're renting things as opposed to if you're actually producing things,
that's a different story.
Yes, and Ayala says her experience in her town was that the
Jews owned the mill and made a lot of money because they
rented it out.
Exactly. You have to imagine that in different scenarios, right, you can
make a lot of money from renting things out.
So in the תוספות *Tosfot* case you're not making, you're just knitting,
you're not making anything? I don't understand. תוספות *Tosfot* says that's when
you don't.
No, you're renting, meaning, meaning you're hiring yourself, you're not selling your
finished product. You're basically like a tailor and you do it for
other people. Okay, תנו רבנן *Tanu Rabbanan*: המשתכר בקנים ובקנקנים *ha-mistacher be-kanim
u-ve-kankanim*, somebody that tries to, you know, basically make their business with
like rods, what? Knick-knacks? Yeah, well no, you'll see the issue here
or with like various vessels, jars, אינו רואה סימן ברכה Siman Beracha.
לעולם *eino roeh siman beracha le-olam*. Will never be blessed. Why? מאי
טעמא *Mai ta'ama*? כיון דנפיש אפחזייהו *Keivan de-nafish ap-chazeihu*, because their bulk
is large. Their volume is large. So what? שלטא בהו עינא *Shalta
beihu eina*, so everybody sees you have these, you know, huge trucks
filled with wares and therefore you get an עין הרע *ayin hara*
because people are jealous. So that's a different reason than we might
have guessed.
Don't own a soda distribution business.
I guess. תנו רבנן *Tanu Rabbanan*: תגרי סימטא ומגדלי בהמה דקה *tagrei
simta u-megadlei beheima daka*, people that sell, there's תגר *tagar* again, and
סימטא *simta* in the marketplace, so people that have like little show,
you know, little booths in the marketplace, and people that grow, that
raise small animals meaning like sheep, grazing animals, וקוצצי אילנות טובות *ve-kotzei
ilanos tovos*, and people in the business of cutting down beautiful trees
like talk about like the, you know, deforestation, and you're doing it,
you know, for the wood, ונותנין עיניהם בחלק יפה *ve-nosnin eineihem be-chelek
yafe*, or people that are always trying to grab the bigger, the
nicer portion, אינו רואה סימן ברכה Siman Beracha לעולם *eino roeh siman
beracha le-olam*. Will never see a ברכה *beracha*. מאי טעמא *Mai ta'ama*?
דתהו אינשי *de-tohu inshi*, people are astounded, right? So you, so meaning
by the marketplace you get the עין הרע *ayin hara*, you're exposed
to everybody, and these, and the by the sheep that was always
something that was everybody רש״י *Rashi* says would complain because they would
always graze in fields that weren't theirs, and the idea of cutting
down these beautiful trees, people are saying what the hell are you
doing cutting down these beautiful trees, you know? So,
and the guy that's always grabbing the nicer portion, same type of
a concern that people get.
So it's more about the public concern than anything? I don't know.
Yeah, it could be that they're all in the market.
I don't know. I don't know. I am finishing this. תנו רבנן
*Tanu Rabbanan*: ארבע פרוטות אין בהם סימן ברכה Siman Beracha. לעולם *Arba
prutos ein bahem siman beracha le-olam*. There are four פרוטות *prutos* and
so again it's like things that get paid for very like, you
know, with pennies, like small, you know, that it's already if it's
a low wage you're most likely not going to get a big
סימן ברכה *siman beracha*. What are these four types of sort of
tasks
that have this low pay that you'll never see a ברכה *beracha*?
שכר כותבין *Schar kosvin*, the fee that you pay for people that
write, we'll see write what, ושכר מתורגמין *ve-schar meturgamin*, the pay that
you pay for the people that do the translation. רש״י *Rashi* says
that it means not the translation of the קריאת התורה *kriat ha-Torah*,
but when somebody would give a שיעור *shiur*, they would speak low
and then this guy would be like the loudspeaker and he would
repeat it very loudly to everybody. ושכר יתומים *Ve-schar yesomim*, the fees
that you get for handling the estate of orphans. You know, sometimes
an executor for a serious estate can make a very big, a
lot of money off of that. ומעות הבאות ממדינת הים *U-ma'ot ha-ba'ot
mi-medinat ha-yam*, and investing your money in, you know, overseas. So all
of that, that's not exactly a פרוטה *pruta*. It's interesting it's. Anyway,
בשלמא שכר מתורגמנים, I get why that the translators or the loudspeakers
don't get סימן ברכה משום דמחזי כשכר שבת Mishum DeMechzei KeSechar Shabbos
because, you know, obviously you'll do it in a way that's halachically
accepted, but it doesn't look appropriate. Looks like you're getting paid for
working on Shabbos, right? I think it was Norman Lamm that said
it was only once he stopped being a shul rabbi, he no
longer had to work on Shabbos. So, you know,
these are the people that look like they're getting paid for work
on Shabbos. ומעות יתומים, UMaos Yesomim, money for, in, for sort of
overseeing the estate of orphans. אינמי לאו בני מחילה נינהו, Inami Lav
Bnei Mechila Ninhu, if they are minors, not just orphans but minors,
they can't be מוחל. Mochel. So if you, if you misuse their
funds, then there'll be like גזל. Gezel. There's not even, oh well,
you know, they'll forgive me because I'm doing it in good faith.
מעות הבאות ממדינת הים, Maos HaBaos MiMedinas HaYam, investing your money overseas,
משום דלאו כל יומא מתרחש ניסא, Mishum DeLav Kol Yoma Misrachesh Nisa,
because, you know, if it's particularly in like boats that are going
to be bringing wares from overseas, so, you know, there was often
a lot of, you know, a lot of pirates and storms and
there's a lot of boats at the bottom of the Atlantic and
or the bottom of the Mediterranean, I don't know. Anyway, so you
can't always rely on a miracle. אלא שכר כותבים מאי טעמא? Ella
Sechar Kosvim Mai Taama? What about why is it not good enterprise
to make money doing scribing? So אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, Amar
Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Levi, כ"ד תעניות ישבו אנשי כנסת הגדולה, Chaf Daled
Taaniyos Yashvu Anshei Knesses HaGedola,
so twenty-four fasts the people of the Great Assembly sat על כותבי
ספרים תפילין ומזוזות. Al Kosvei Sfarim Tfillin UMezuzos. They prayed to God
that for people that make their living by writing ספרי תורה תפילין
ומזוזות, Sifrei Torah Tfillin UMezuzos, שלא יתעשרו, SheLo Yisasheru, that they should
never become rich. Why? שאילמלא מתעשרין אין כותבין, Sheilmalei Misaashrin Ein Kosvin,
because if it was too much of a profit, then they wouldn't
do it. We need this to be,
so we need them to keep on doing it, and if it
was too profitable then nobody would do it. Presumably or else you
would have to pay a lot of money to get your ספר
תורה תפילין ומזוזות. Sefer Torah Tfillin UMezuzos. So somehow it was מאת
השם Meis HaShem that they should do it without ever getting too
rich so that they can be affordable and they'll have to keep
on doing it. And just with that, we'll end with two more
lines. תנו רבנן: כותבי ספרים תפילין ומזוזות הן ותגריהן ותגרי תגריהן, Kosvei
Sfarim Tfillin UMezuzos Hein VeTagreihen VeTagrei Tagreihen, they and their sellers and
their, you know, retailers, wholesalers, וכל העוסקים במלאכת שמים, VeChol HaOskim BiMeleches
Shamayim, anybody who involves themselves in this heavenly pursuit, לאתויי מוכרי תכלת,
Laasuyei Mochrei Techeiles, including those that sell תכלת. Techeiles. Normally this type
of introduction ends with
עוסק במצוה ופטור מן קריאת שמע מן התפילה מן התפילין. Oseik BeMitzva
UPatur Min Krias Shema Min HaTfilla Min HaTfillin. That's how the statement
ends in ברכות. Brachos. Here the statement ends with, what do you
say about all these people, these scribes and whatnot? אינם רואים סימן
ברכה לעולם. Einam Ro'in Siman Beracha LeOlam. They'll never get, they'll never
be too profitable in their business. ואם עוסקים לשמה, VeIm Oskim Lishma,
and now a nice tie-in to the לשמה. But if they're doing
it לשם שמים, Leshem Shamayim, not to make money, then רואים, Ro'in,
then they will see a סימן ברכה. Whole reason they won't see
a סימן ברכה is that they shouldn't stop writing. But if you're
doing it לשם שמים, Leshem Shamayim, even if you make a lot
of money, you'll keep on producing it and therefore you'll be able
to see a סימן ברכה. Okay, let's get rich together.